Guide to the Julius Hartt collection ARCH059
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Julius Hartt collection
1869-1981
undated
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
ARCH059
1.25 Linear Feet (3 containers)
This collection consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, and personal items belonging, or pertaining, to Julius Hartt.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to all researchers.
Biographical Note
Julius Hartt founded the Julius Hartt School of Music with Moshe Paranov in 1920. The Julius Hartt School eventually became the Hartt School of the University of Hartford. Hartt also served as music critic for the Hartford Times.
Julius Hartt was born in 1869 in Boston, Massachusetts, son of the Reverend Aaron Hartt, a Baptist minister and Jennie Marr Hartt. As a child, Julius displayed unusual musical talent. He studied music in Berlin and began his teaching career there before going to Vienna.
Hartt returned to Boston in 1903 and taught there until coming to Hartford to serve as organist of the Asylum Hill Congregational Church. Hartt married Jennie Hall in 1898. The couple had three children and five grandchildren. His daughter Pauline known as "Dot" or "Dottie" married Moshe Paranov.
Scope and Contents
This is a small collection of original material documenting the life of Julius Hartt, founder of the Hartt School of Music. The contents of this collection are mostly personal, reflecting the family and social activities of Julius Hartt.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series: I. Correspondence, II. Personal Materials, III. Writings, and IV. Photographs.
Photographs; Correspondence; Personal papers; Musical criticism; Periodicals; Hartt, Julius; Julius Hartt School of Music; Hartt, Jane; Hartt, Pauline Lilly; Hartt, Harriet; Berkman, Aaron; Paranov, Moshe, 1895-1994; Hartt, Robert; Lilly, Pauline; Bloch, Ivan; Engel, Carl, 1883-1944; Kahn, Irene; Berkman, Samuel; Gauthier, Eva, 1885-1958
- Correspondence
  - Letters to Jane and all, from Berlin, 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Postcards to Robert Hartt, 1902-1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Jane and others, 1902-1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Postcards to Mrs. Julius Hartt, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Postcards to Pauline L. Hartt, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Postcards to Pauline Lilly, 1903 - 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Harriet and Pauline, 1912 - 1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Postcards from family, 1903 - 1921, undated; undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Postcards to Harriet Hartt, 1904, 1912, undated; 1912; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Julius Hartt, 1905 - 1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Harriet and J. Hartt from W. Wilson, 1905, 1921 - 1922; 1921 - 1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Carl Engel to Julius Hartt, Moshe Paranov, Pauline Hartt Paranov, 1920 - 1922, undated; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Harriet (Giz) from Aaron Berkman, 1921, undated; undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Eva Gauthier letters to Julius Hartt, 1921, undated; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters to daughter Harriet from Moshe, 1922, undated; undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters to the Boston Music Company, 1921 Apr 26 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hyde Richarel, 1926 - 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Son, Robert Letters to Pa and Dot, 1923 - 1939, 1980, undated; 1980; undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Julius Hartt from Ivan Bloch, 1927 May 22, undated; undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Condolence Letters, 1949 Sep (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Personal materials
  - Signature Plate, Book Cover, Course Catalog, Business Card, 1834, 1901, 1948; 1901; undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Autographs, 1882 - 1888 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Wedding, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Copy of Exercises in Harmony, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Julius Hartt son Robert, 1901 - 1981, undated; undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Berlin Concert Programs, 1902 - 1904, 1919, undated; 1919; undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Leases and Mortgages, 1903 - 1927 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1907 - 1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mason Hamlin, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Programs- Julius Hartt, ogran; Harriet Shaw, Harp, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Concert Programs- U.S., Unity Hall, 1911 - 1933, undated; undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - News Clips, 1914 - 1921, undated; undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Obituaries, 1942 Sep (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Biography, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Harriet Hartt Obituaries, 1994 Mar 4 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Program- Julius Hartt; Piano, Cooke; Gamerdinger, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Program Goodwill Club Orchestra, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Copper Plates, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Writings
  - Reviews, 1869 - 1942 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters of a Musician, 1917 Dec - 1918 Apr (Box 3, Folder 13-18)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains clippings of Julius Hartt's Hartford Times articles entitled "Letters of a Musician." The series included: I. To a Business Man, II. To a Lady, III. To a Young Man, IV. To a Musical Critic, V. To a Young Musician, VII. To a Young Lady. It is unknown if a sixth letter was ever written or published (it may have been omitted, or there may have been a numbering error).
  - Letters of a Musician - Myron Schwager, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    This file contains an article about Julius Hartt's "Letters of a Musician" -- Schwager, Myron. "Julius Hartt: Letters of a Musician." The American Music Teacher (Nov-Dec 1985): 48-50.
  - Temperament and Character in Ernest Bloch, 1928 Nov 10 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - West Hartford News-Julius Hartt Reviews, 1931 Oct 23 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Casual Affirmations of a Pianist, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Photographs
  - Julius Hartt with Eva Gavtier, I. Kahn, S. Berkman, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Various Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)